<bookinfo> 
	<title>Debian Pure Blends</title> 

	<author> 
		<firstname>Andreas</firstname> 
		<surname>Tille</surname> 
		<affiliation> 
			<address>
				<email>tille@debian.org</email>
			</address> 
		</affiliation> 
	</author> 

	<revhistory>
		<revision>
			<revnumber>v1</revnumber>
		  	<date>19 Jun 2013</date>
		  	<!--<authorinitials></authorinitials>
		  	<revremark></revremark> -->
		</revision>
	</revhistory>

	<copyright> 
		<year>2004 - 2011</year> <holder>Andreas Tille, Ben Armstrong</holder> 
	</copyright> 

	<legalnotice>
    <title>Copyright</title>
	    <para>
	      This manual is Free Software; you may redistribute it and/or
	      modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as
	      published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.0, or
	      (at your option) any later version.
	    </para>

	    <para>
	      This is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
	      <emphasis>without any warranty</emphasis>; without even the implied warranty
	      of merchantability or fitness for a particular purpose.  See the
	      GNU General Public License for more details.
	    </para>

	    <para>
	      A copy of the GNU General Public License is available
	      on the World Wide Web at <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"/>.  You
	      can also obtain it by writing to the Free Software Foundation,
	      Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110, USA.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	      You can find the source of this article 
	      <ulink url="http://git.debian.org/?p=blends/blends.git;a=tree;f=doc/en">in the Git repository at git.debian.org</ulink>.
	      It is also available as Debian package blends-doc<!-- <package>blends-doc</package>. -->
	    </para>

	    <para>
	      A <ulink url="debian-blends.en.pdf">printable version in PDF format</ulink> will be built
	           from time to time.
	    </para>
    </legalnotice>

	<abstract> 
		<para>
			This paper is intended for people who are interested in the philosophy
			of Debian Pure Blends (in short "Blends" if it is used clearly in
			internal Debian context), and the technique that is used to manage
			those projects.  For those who are familiar with the concept of Custom
			Debian Distributions: We just found a new name for this concept
			because the old name just not expressed what actually is done.  It is
			explained in detail why Blends are not forks from Debian, but reside
			completely inside the Debian GNU/Linux distribution, and which
			advantages can be enjoyed by taking this approach.  The concept of
			metapackages and user role based menus is explained.  In short: This
			document describes why Debian Pure Blends are important to the
			vitality and quality of Debian.
		</para> 
	</abstract> 
</bookinfo>